<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugo on stuart crust</title>
    <link>https://stuartcrust.com/categories/hugo/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hugo on stuart crust</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://stuartcrust.com/categories/hugo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Third Time&#39;s The Charm</title>
      <link>https://stuartcrust.com/2018/09/third-times-the-charm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stuartcrust.com/2018/09/third-times-the-charm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;document&#34;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been meaning to start blogging for a while. Not even blogging &lt;em&gt;consistently&lt;/em&gt;, just writing some long-form-ish pieces on projects that I&#39;ve been working on, things I&#39;ve learned, or things that I might want for my own reference. I&#39;ve tried at least twice before - once when I purchased this domain back in December of &lt;em&gt;2013&lt;/em&gt; and again at the end of 2016 - and as evidenced by the utter lack of content it&#39;s pretty clear I haven&#39;t been successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a real attempt to begin publishing at the end of 2016 with the release of that year&#39;s &lt;a class=&#34;reference external&#34; href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com/2016/&#34;&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt;, but coursework kept me pretty busy and I never managed to finish and publish any of the posts I was working on at the time. I&#39;ll probably revisit some of them, clean them up, and post them - if I still remember what I was writing about - and the rest I may throw into a backlog so that if I ever run into a simiar topic again I can incorporate my draft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason I&#39;m giving it another try now is I&#39;m taking a course that specifically focuses on open source and includes a requirement that the students blog about their work and experiences as they gain exposure to the open source community. I&#39;m &lt;a class=&#34;reference external&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/0xazure&#34;&gt;not exactly a stranger&lt;/a&gt; to open source work, but I haven&#39;t had time to be as active as I would like to be so this course is giving me a good excuse to commit more time to getting involved and getting my hands dirty with some contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the technical side, this site is built using the static site generator &lt;a class=&#34;reference external&#34; href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;ve been learning a lot about the ins and outs of Hugo&#39;s project structure as I set this blog up, but so far I&#39;m pretty happy with the results. Hugo is written in &lt;a class=&#34;reference external&#34; href=&#34;https://golang.org/&#34;&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt;, the Google-sponsored C/++ replacement, and Hugo has a very active community that keeps improving the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One issue that I did run into was some confusion over themes in Hugo. Each Hugo site has a &lt;tt class=&#34;docutils literal&#34;&gt;config.toml&lt;/tt&gt; that sets parameters for how the static site content should be generated. Those parameters also include information like social media links that get embedded in certain parts of the Hugo theme that structures the site content and controls the look and feel. Unfortunately, there don&#39;t seem to be standard keys for many of these parameters, so the key name for your GitHub or StackOverflow account information needs to be updated if you decide to change your site theme. You can see some of the work I had to do &lt;a class=&#34;reference external&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/0xazure/0xazure/commit/ed9a74d58acbcd49f0be613cfd14dbefb725a842&#34;&gt;in this commit&lt;/a&gt; to update these values when I changed my theme from &lt;a class=&#34;reference external&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/zyro/hyde-x&#34;&gt;hyde-x&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a class=&#34;reference external&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/dplesca/purehugo&#34;&gt;purehugo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been keeping my eye on other static site generators as well, but Hugo is very popular and has a lot of great community contributions and support so I&#39;ll be using it for a while yet. Now that things are up and running I might take a stab at customizing my theme a little bit more, an opportunity I wouldn&#39;t have if Hugo and its public themes weren&#39;t open source. Where many static site generators use things like &lt;a class=&#34;reference external&#34; href=&#34;http://handlebarsjs.com/&#34;&gt;Handlebars&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a class=&#34;reference external&#34; href=&#34;https://shopify.github.io/liquid/&#34;&gt;Liquid&lt;/a&gt; for templating, Hugo actually delegates straight to the built-in &lt;a class=&#34;reference external&#34; href=&#34;https://golang.org/pkg/text/template/&#34;&gt;text.template&lt;/a&gt; package in Go. This makes it immediately familiar to most Go developers, but I haven&#39;t had the opportunity to use Go much - especially recently - so I&#39;ll likely be spending a lot of time reading the documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this third attempt will be the one that sticks. Stay tuned for more posts on topics including &lt;a class=&#34;reference external&#34; href=&#34;categories/open-source&#34;&gt;open source&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&#34;reference external&#34; href=&#34;categories/nodejs&#34;&gt;NodeJS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&#34;reference external&#34; href=&#34;categories/rust&#34;&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&#34;reference external&#34; href=&#34;categories/functional-programming&#34;&gt;functional programming&lt;/a&gt;, and anything else I might get up to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
